<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="out/McAllen.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="out/McAllen.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The History of Temple Emanuel: Birth of a Congregation</title>
            <title type="sub">TEI Encoding of Temple Emanuel 50th Anniversary</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Gabrielle Lyle</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Station, TX</pubPlace>
            <date>Fall 2019</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This work was provided to the publisher by Temple Emanuel, it can also be found at the Briscoe Center for American History at the University of Texas at Austin.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
                  <bibl>
                     <author></author>
                     <title>Temple Emanuel 50 Years 1948-19988</title>
                     <pubPlace>McAllen, Texas</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Temple Emanuel</publisher>
                     <date when="1998">1998</date>
                     <citedRange></citedRange>
                     <biblScope unit="page">12-18</biblScope>
                  </bibl>    
            </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="section">
            <head type="main">History of Temple Emanuel</head>
            <head type="sub">Birth of a Congregation</head>
         <p>The year was <date when="1948">1948</date>. It was a remarkable time for Jews all over the world. Gathered around radios
            in millions of homes, people held their breaths as <orgName ref="#un">U.N.</orgName> votes were tallied on a resolution to establish the
            <placeName ref="#isra">State of Israel</placeName>. Cheers erupted in every comer of the globe as news of the birth of a Jewish homeland
            flooded the airwaves.</p>
         <p> A healing process had begun. Jewish communities of the Diaspora began to channel their grief
            and anger over the recent Holocaust into a reaffirmation of faith and a renewed commitment to preserve a
            precious heritage for future generations.</p>
         <p>Deep in the southernmost reaches of <placeName ref="#tex">Texas</placeName>, a group of visionaries was making good on that commitment.
            Twenty-eight Jewish families gathered together at the home of <persName ref="#rwol">Rachael</persName> and <persName ref="#cwol">Charles Wolf</persName>
               in
               <pb n="12"/>
            <placeName ref="#phar">Pharr, Texas</placeName>, to begin plans to form a temple. The group agreed that the temple would be reform.
            <persName ref="#awes">Adolph Westerman</persName> and <persName ref="#slac">Sam Lack</persName> volunteered to spearhead the fundraising drive. Construction began,
            and on <date when="1949-03-20">March 20, 1949</date>, one year after the historic <orgName ref="#un">U.N.</orgName> vote, <placeName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</placeName> was born in <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen, Texas</placeName>.</p>
         <p>The new <placeName ref="#tema">Temple</placeName>had been a long time in coming. Apparently, the first Jewish congregation was
            a joint community in <placeName ref="#bvil">Brownsville</placeName> and <placeName ref="#mata">Matamoros</placeName>. According to a letter written in by <persName ref="#bkow">Benjamin
               Kowalski</persName>, mayor of <placeName ref="#bvil">Brownsville</placeName>, on <date when="1876-07-12">July 12, 1876</date>, the "Jehudims of both cities ... formed a <orgName ref="#hbas">Hebrew
                  Benevolent Association</orgName>," and the "feast and fast days ... were "held in <placeName ref="#mata">Matamoros</placeName>, where they have a
            Torah."</p>
         <p>In the early part of the 20th century, most Jews in the <placeName ref="#urgv">upper Valley</placeName>lived in <placeName ref="#merc">Mercedes</placeName> and <placeName ref="#phar">Pharr</placeName>,
            then the two largest cities in the region. To celebrate the High Holy Days, the people in the <placeName ref="#urgv">upper Valley</placeName>
            rented a building in <placeName ref="#merc">Mercedes</placeName> where all Jewish families would come to worship. In <date when="1935">1935</date>, <placeName ref="#tbis">Temple Beth
               Israel</placeName> was erected in <placeName>Mercedes</placeName> for the Jewish communities of the <placeName ref="#urgv">upper Valley</placeName> and <placeName ref="#harl">Harlingen</placeName>.</p>
         <p>Soon, the railroad began bringing greater numbers of people to <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName> and the surrounding
            communities of <placeName ref="#miss">Mission</placeName>and <placeName ref="#phar">Pharr</placeName>. Soldiers stationed here spent their money in town and business
            began booming. The fertile soil, abundant water, and year-round mild climate lured many newcomers.
            The Jewish population in <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName> began to grow. Families came together, not only to worship, but to
            socialize and educate their children. <orgName ref="#ssch">Sunday School</orgName> classes were held each week in private homes. The
            first class was held in the home of <persName ref="#sede">Sophye Edelstein</persName> and students included <persName ref="#nalb">Norma Westerman Albert</persName>,
            <persName ref="#bfar">Betty Jean Edelstein Farb</persName> and <persName ref="#hlew">Hilda Chaleff Lewin</persName>. The first confirmation class in <placeName ref="#merc">Mercedes</placeName> included
            several of the children from those early <orgName ref="#ssch">Sunday School</orgName> classes.</p>
         <p>By the <date>late 1940s</date>, there were so many Jewish families in <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName> and surrounding towns, that
            a new temple was necessary to provide local facilities for worship, education and activities.
            Construction on <placeName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</placeName> began in <date>1948</date>. The first congregation had 60 members. <persName ref="#awes">Aldolph
               Westerman</persName> served as the first President, <persName ref="#mlut">Max Lutz</persName> was Vice President, <persName ref="#mada">Moe Adams</persName> was Treasurer, and
            <persName ref="#sede">Mrs. J. Edelstein</persName> was Secretary.</p>
            <p>The temple building, designed by architect <persName ref="#zrik">Zeb Rike</persName> of <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName> and constructed by <orgName ref="#wmec">Wm. E. Crawford</orgName>
               of <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName>, was dedicated on <date when="1949-03-20">March 20, 1949</date>. Rabbis <persName ref="#ygel">Yonah B. Geller</persName>, of <placeName ref="#tbni">Temple B'Nai
                  Israel</placeName>, and <persName ref="#swol">Sidney Wolf</persName>, of <placeName ref="#tbel">Temple Beth El</placeName> in <placeName ref="#cchr">Corpus Christi</placeName>, opened the services that day with the dedication
               of the cornerstone. <persName ref="#fche">Rev. Francis X. Cheney</persName>, Pastor of <placeName ref="#sjec">St. John's Episcopal Church</placeName> in <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName>,
            gave the invocation in the auditorium. <persName ref="#lher">Louis Herman</persName>, lay religious leader of the congregation, welcomed
            guests and compared the formation and establishment of the <placeName ref="#isra">nation of Israel</placeName> with the work of the
            congregation, culminating in the erection of the temple-a temple at which members of all faiths would
            be welcome.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#swol">Rabbi Wolf</persName> spoke on "Mine House Shall Be Called a House of Prayer for All People." <persName ref="#ygel">Rabbi
            Geller's</persName> message pointed out the three phases of synagogue influence-the synagogue to the individual,
               the synagogue to the community, and the individual to the synagogue. <persName ref="#mwes">Mrs. Adolph Westerman</persName>,
               <pb n="13"/>
            president of the <orgName ref="#tesh">Sisterhood</orgName>, performed the ceremony of lighting the eternal light. <persName ref="#ssol">Mrs. Sandra
               Solomon</persName> sang "The Lord is My Light," accompanied by <persName ref="#hgue">Miss Hilda Guerra</persName>. And <persName ref="#hspr">Rev. Hearne Spruce</persName>,
            pastor of the <placeName ref="#cotz">Church of the Nazarene</placeName>, spoke on behalf of the <orgName ref="#mial">Ministerial Alliance</orgName>.</p>
         <p>For the first seven years after <orgName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</orgName> was established, the men of the congregation
            took turns as lay-readers, as there were no prospects for an ordained rabbi. <persName ref="#lher">Louis Herman</persName>, one of the
            founders of the congregation, served as lay-reader until his death. Finally, in <date when="1956">1956</date>, <persName ref="#hett">Rabbi H.B.
               Ettinger</persName> became Temple Emanuel's first rabbi. He was followed ·over the years by <persName ref="#wgor">Rabbi William
                  Gordon</persName>, <persName ref="#ltur">Rabbi Leo E. Turitz</persName>, <persName ref="#mman">Rabbi Michael Manson</persName>, <persName ref="#mbel">Rabbi Maynard Bell</persName>, <persName ref="#jels">Rabbi Jeffrey Elson</persName>,
            <persName ref="#bdan">Rabbi Bryan Daniels</persName>, and our current Rabbi, <persName ref="#dlip">David Lipper</persName>.</p>
         <p>A six room <orgName ref="#ssch">Sunday School</orgName> facility was eventually constructed at the west end of the <placeName ref="#tema">Temple</placeName>
            property, followed by yet another wing of classrooms. The <placeName ref="#tema">Temple</placeName> itself was remodeled and enlarged
            in <date when="1972">1972</date> and <date when="1973">1973</date>, when <persName ref="#lkro">Leonard Kroman</persName> was president of the congregation. <persName ref="#slac">Sam Lack</persName> and <persName ref="#mlut">Max Lutz</persName>
            spearheaded the remodeling. Seats replaced the pews in the santuary and were "sold" to the membership
            to raise funds. Additional seating was added and the bima, or pulpit, was improved. Walnut
            paneling replaced the wainscoting in the social hall. The kitchen was enlarged, new appliances were
            added, and a library was built.</p>
         <p>Over the years the congregation of <orgName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</orgName> grew and diversified. The community
            became a melting pot, welcoming Jewish settlers from all over the country and the world. Three families-
            the <persName ref="#jnew">Jacobo Newman</persName> family, the <persName ref="#mtem">Moises Tempkin</persName> family, and the <persName ref="#mbor">Meyer Borofsky</persName> family became
            the first of the congregation's <placeName ref="#mexi">Mexico</placeName> contingency. That contingency would blossom into a
            vital part of the <orgName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</orgName> congregation. The families lived in <placeName ref="#reyn">Reynosa</placeName>, but sent their children
            to religious school in <placeName ref="#merc">Mercedes</placeName> and, later, in <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName>. <persName ref="#cbor">Cecilia Borofsky</persName> and her mother, <persName ref="#brab">Bertha Rabinovich</persName>, had come from <placeName ref="#lith">Lithuania</placeName> and settled in <placeName ref="#mexi">Mexico</placeName> in the 1920s. After <persName ref="#mbor">Meyer Borofaky's</persName>
            death, <persName ref="#cbor">Cecilia</persName> moved to<placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName>  with her mother and her son, <persName ref="#jbor">Jack</persName>. She married <persName ref="#isha">Irving Shapiro</persName> in
            <date when="1954">1954</date>.</p>
         <p>And so were born second generations. The new generations of members were bar and bat
            mitzvahed, confirmed, married, and eventually had children of their own. Many of those young members
            left the <placeName ref="#rgv">Valley</placeName>to go to college. But one by one, they returned to raise their families here.</p>
         <p>Now, 50 years after those first 28 families met to plan a future, <orgName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</orgName> has matured
            into a congregation of 180 families. And as we approach a new era for our congregation, we are filled
            with the kind of excitement and anticipation that our founders must have felt as they watched their
            dream become a reality. Indeed, the next 50 years will surely bring the realization of many new
            dreams-dreams that simply would not exist had it not been for the vision and determination of those
            first families. We dedicate this momentous anniversary to the founders of <orgName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</orgName>. It is with
            them in mind that we renew our commitment to preserving our precious heritage and making our
            dreams come true.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="15"/>
         <div type="section">
            <p>To be at the Bimah of my Temple is an honor, but to read the inscription in the wall is a blessing.</p>
            <p> "I Have Set The Lord Always Before Me."</p>
            <p>I have read them over and over again. In Shabbat, at a Bat or Bar Mitzvah of my children and my friends children, and in every occasion
               I have attended in the Temple. Within my heart and my soul I am filled with emotion every time I read them and I thank God for the they hold today.</p>
            <p>I am <sic><orig>quiet</orig><reg>quite</reg></sic> sure that the first stone placed to build this Temple was with the <sic><orig>believe</orig><reg>belief</reg></sic> in that inscription, and what was once a dream, became a reality.
               Half a century later we can still head it and follow it's meaning.</p>
            <p>I congratulate my Temple for it's Fiftieth anniversary, but I bless those people who made it possible for this to happen. All of us have 
               contributed for this to happen. Step by step we have formed the Temple's history for the first fifty years, and I am sure that there is within it's walls 
               part of our heats. They say that with bricks you build a House but with love you build a home.</p>
            <p>Every time you cross the Temple's door, I invite you to go to the Bimah and read those words and assure yourself that putting God before
               every thing else brings prosperity.</p>
            <p>For me it's an honor to be able to be <sic><orig>Sisterhood's</orig><reg>the Sisterhood's</reg></sic> president in this great event. I hope and trust in God that this part of our history that we are writing together
               be pleasing in the eyes of our Creator.</p>
            <p>Congratulations Temple Emanuel and lots of happiness to the Family that we all form within our community.</p>
            <p>With Love,</p>
            <p><persName ref= "#scha">Sylvia Chacra</persName></p>
         </div>
         <pb n="16"/>
         <div>
         <head type="main">TEMPLE EMANUEL SISTERHOOD</head>
            <p>The <orgName ref="#tesh">Temple Emanuel Sisterhood</orgName> was organized in <date when="1948-10">October of 1948</date>, with <persName ref="#mwes">Mrs. Adolph
            Westerman</persName> as President. Its purpose-to oversee the religious education of the children of the
            congregation and to coordinate the social and community functions of the Temple. Other officers
            of the newly formed organization were <persName ref="#sede">Mrs. J. Edelstein</persName>, Vice President; <persName ref="#hlew">Mrs. Leroy Lewin</persName>,
               Recording Secretary; <persName ref="#lfal">Mrs. Mike Fallek</persName>, Corresponding Secretary; <persName ref="#ekle">Mrs. Ben Klein</persName>, Treasurer; and
               <persName ref="#lpec">Mrs. L. Peck</persName>, Parliamentarian.</p>
            <p>The first meeting was held in the home of <persName ref="#blac">Mrs. Sam Lack</persName>. <persName ref="#sede">Mrs. Edelstein</persName> was elected
               Superintendent of the <orgName ref="#ssch">Sunday School</orgName>, and <persName ref="#lhaa01">Mrs. J. Haas</persName> was elected Assistant Superintendent.
            Plans were made for a rummage sale to be held the following month at the Berk building on
            Beaumont Avenue and South 15th Street. The first rummage sale raised $541.</p>
            <p>In January 1949, Trustees were appointed. Two-year Trustees were <persName ref="#pwei">Mrs. Morris Weisfeld</persName>,
               <persName ref="#rlut">Mrs. Max Lutz</persName>, <persName ref="#fcha">Mrs. Albert Chaleff</persName> and <persName ref="#clev">Mrs. J. Levine</persName> of <placeName ref="#wesl">Weslaco</placeName>. Three-year Trustees were
               <persName ref="#esch">Mrs. H.I. Schlader</persName> of <placeName ref="#edin">Edinburg</placeName> and <persName ref="#blac">Mrs. Sam Lack</persName>.</p>
            <p>Founders of the <orgName ref="#tesh">Sisterhood</orgName> included <persName ref="#nalb">Norma Albert</persName>, <persName ref="#cbor">Cecilia Borofsky (Shapiro)</persName>, <persName ref="#fcha">Fanny
               Chaleff</persName>, <persName ref="#sede">Sophye Edelstein</persName>, <persName ref="#reis">Rose Eisenberg</persName>, <persName ref="#bfar">Betty Jean Farb</persName>, <persName ref="#egar">Esther Gardner</persName>, <persName ref="#fgel">Frieda Gelfer</persName>, <persName ref="#eger">Evelyn Gerrick</persName>, <persName ref="#agol">Anna Goldberg</persName>, <persName ref="#agra">Anna Grabiner</persName>, <persName ref="#lhaa01">Lilly Haas</persName>, <persName ref="#lhaa02">Lena Haas</persName>, <persName ref="#rhab">Ruth Haberman</persName>, <persName ref="#jhor">Jenny Horvich</persName>,
               <persName ref="#mhir">Marge Hirtenstein</persName>, <persName ref="#dkle">Dorothy Kleban</persName>, <persName ref="#ekle">Esther Klein</persName>, <persName ref="#ckir">Clara Kirsh</persName>, <persName ref="#ekun">Elizabeth Kunik</persName>, <persName ref="#blac">Bea Lack</persName>, <persName ref="#clev">Clara
                  Levine</persName>, <persName ref="#hlew">Hilda Lewin</persName>, <persName ref="#rlut">Ruth Lutz</persName>, <persName ref="#zmar" >Zebella Markham</persName>, <persName ref="#jmil">Jane Miller</persName>, <persName ref="#rmer">Rae Merkin</persName>, <persName ref="#rmor">Rose Morganstem</persName>,
               <persName ref="#gpan">Gertrude Pantie</persName>, <persName ref="#esch">Esther Schlader</persName>, <persName ref="#rsid">Ruthie Sidelnik</persName>, <persName ref="#bspi">Bertha Spielberg</persName>, <persName ref="#mten">Miriam Tenenbaum</persName>, <persName ref="#ewei">Elise Weil</persName>, <persName ref="#isin">Ida Singer</persName>, <persName ref="#pwei">Pauline Weisfeld</persName>, <persName ref="#mwes">Mary Westerman</persName>, <persName ref="#rwol">Rachael Wolff</persName>, <persName ref="#leva">Lenore Evans</persName>, <persName ref="#pgol">Pearl Goldberg</persName>, <persName ref="#fgre">Fanny Greenfeld</persName>, <persName ref="#nrat">Natalie Ratkin</persName> and <persName ref="#fste">Frances Steinman</persName>.</p>
         <p>The first confirmation class of <orgName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</orgName> was confirmed on June 1, 1952 and
            included <persName ref="#alev">Alvin Levine</persName> of <placeName ref="#wesl">Weslaco</placeName>, <persName ref="#rwei">Rose Marie Weisfeld</persName> of <placeName ref="#phar">Pharr</placeName>, <persName ref="#dger">Dolores Gerrick</persName> of <placeName ref="#phar">Pharr</placeName>,
            <persName ref="#mfal">Mildred Fallek</persName> and <persName ref="#bkun">Burton Kunik</persName> of <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName>, and was taught by <persName ref="#asaf">Mrs. Alex Safir</persName>. <persName ref="#ygel">Rabbi Y. Geller</persName>
            of <placeName ref="#cchr">Corpus Christi</placeName> officiated.</p>
            <p>The Temple's first historian was <persName ref="#nalb">Norma Albert</persName>. Her daughter, <persName ref="#salb">Sharon Margaret Albert</persName> was
               the first baby named at <placeName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</placeName> on <date when="1949-10-26">October 26, 1949</date>. <persName ref="#msch">Maxine Schlader</persName> was the first
               bride married in the <placeName ref="#tema">Temple</placeName> to <persName ref="#bhor">Bernie Horwitz</persName>.</p>
         <p>One of <orgName ref="#tesh">Sisterhood's</orgName> earliest and proudest achievements was working with the <orgName ref="#ncjw">Council of
            Jewish Women</orgName> to ready a home for a refugee family who came to <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName> from a displaced persons
            camp in <placeName ref="#germ">Germany</placeName>. <persName ref="#jdav">Jack</persName> and <persName ref="#edav">Ester Davidson</persName>, along with their daughter <persName ref="#rdav">Ruth</persName>, were brought to
            <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName> by the Jewish community through agencies of the <orgName ref="#uja">United Jewish Appeal</orgName>. They lived in
            <placeName ref="#mcal">McAllen</placeName> for several years before moving to <placeName ref="#hous">Houston</placeName>.</p>
         <p>In 1954, <orgName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</orgName> affiliated with the <orgName ref="#uahc">Union of American Hebrew Congregations</orgName>.
            The <placeName ref="#tema">Temple</placeName> received its charter at a dinner meeting on <date when="1954-03-28">March 28, 1954</date>. <persName ref="#lstil">Rabbi Leo J. Stillpass</persName> of
            <placeName ref="#gal">Galveston</placeName> presented the union charter to <persName ref="#rwei2">Russell Weil</persName>, president of the congregation. There were
            55 families in the congregation at that time.</p>
            <p>Fifty years after that first meeting in the home of <persName ref="#blac">Mrs. Sam Lack</persName>, the <orgName ref="#tesh">Temple Emanuel
            Sisterhood</orgName> is as active and vibrant as ever.</p>
            <pb n="17"/>
         <p>The <orgName ref="#mvch">McAllen-Valley Chapter</orgName> is also working to raise community awareness about such crucial
            issues as domestic violence and breast cancer. The highly successful Walk-a-Thon in 1997 was one
            of the best examples of the chapter's breast cancer awareness initiatives. With 130 participants, it
            not only allowed <orgName ref="#hada">Hadassah</orgName> to spread the word about the importance of early cancer detection and
            prevention, it also raised substantial funds.</p>
         <p>As we celebrate this most important anniversary of <orgName ref="#tema">Temple Emanuel</orgName>, the <orgName ref="#mvch">McAllen-Valley Chapter
            of Hadassah</orgName> looks forward to the next 50 years-working together for a cohesive, prolific and productive
            partnership.</p>
            <byline>Robbie Hohenstein</byline>
         </div>
         <pb n="18"/>
         <div>
            <head type="main"><orgName ref="#hada">HADASSAH</orgName></head>
         <p>The <orgName ref="#mvch">McAllen Valley Chapter of Hadassah</orgName> was organized as the <orgName ref= "#vch">Valley Chapter of Hadassah</orgName> in
            the fall of <date when="1952">1952</date> by <persName ref="#mwes">Mrs. Adolph (Mary) Westerman</persName>, with the help of <persName ref="#rham">Mrs. Rose Hamovit</persName> and <persName ref="#mcat">Mrs. Morris Catchman</persName> of <placeName ref="#hous">Houston</placeName>. <persName ref="#mwes">Mary</persName> became the first President and served in that capacity for two
            years. The chapter started with 33 members. By the end of her term, it had grown to 51 members.</p>
         <p>Although there was no quota the first year, the chapter had a linen shower and sent a large box
            of linens to the <placeName ref="#haho">Hadassah hospital</placeName> in <placeName ref="#isra">Israel</placeName> and earned and donated $100 to <orgName ref="#yali">Youth Aliyah</orgName>.</p>
         <p>In those first years, the chapter did a lot of community service. It participated in the <placeName ref="#rcdc">Red Cross Donor Center</placeName>, did child welfare work, and made dressings for the <orgName ref="#acs">Cancer Society</orgName>. This enabled it to
            become well known in the community. The chapter also sold Israel Bonds to its members.</p>
            <p>The next President of the chapter was <persName ref="#tgol">Mrs. Tilly Goldstein</persName>, who served from <date when="1954">1954</date> to <date when="1956">1956</date>.
            An annual barbeque was initiated during her administration. It started out earning $300 and, by its
            final year, earned about $5,000 and involved the entire Jewish commuunity.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#egar">Mrs. Esther Gardner Goldberg</persName> served as President from <date notBefore="1956" notAfter="1958">1956-58</date>, followed by <persName ref="#grab">Mrs. George
            Rabinowitz</persName>, who served from <date when="1958">1958</date> to <date>1960</date>. It was during her administration that the chapter sponsored
            the first Bonds for <placeName ref="#isra">Israel</placeName> drive and got its first five life members.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#nalb">Mrs. Norma Albert</persName> presided from <date when="1960">1960</date> to <date when="1962">1962</date>. During her administration, the chapter was
            still working for the <orgName ref="#acs">American Cancer Society</orgName> and was presented an award for outstanding service.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#dros">Mrs. David Rosenthal</persName> served as President from <date when="1962">1962</date> to <date when="1964">1964</date>, during which time the chapter
            hosted its first Regional Conference in <date when="1964-04">April of 1964</date>.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#cher">Mrs. Charlene Hertz</persName> served the term of President in <date notBefore="1964" notAfter="1966">1964-66</date>. In <date>1965</date>, the chapter celebrated
            its Bat Mitzvah anniversary with a special dinner. At this time, the Henrietta Szold Award was presented
            to the chapter by the <orgName ref="#nibo">National Israel Bond Organization</orgName> in recognition of its outstanding
            record-the first award of its kind in the nation!</p>
            <p><persName ref="#mfri">Mrs. Marvin Friedman</persName> served from 1966 to 1968 and <persName ref="#gwei">Mrs. Gilbert Weisberg</persName> from <date when="1968">1968</date> to
               <date when="1970">1970</date>. <persName ref="#bwit">Mrs. Bert Witte</persName> served in 1970-72. <persName>Mrs. Al Levine</persName> served as President in <date notBefore="1972" notAfter="1974">1972-74</date>, and in
               <date when="1973-04">April of 1973</date>, the chapter hosted its second Regional Conference. <persName ref="#lmar">Mrs. Leonard Marcus</persName> was the
               <pb n="19"/>
            chapter President from <date when="1974">1974</date> to <date when="1976">1976</date>.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#mlev">Mrs. Myrna Levin</persName> presided over the chapter from 1976 to 1978. It was during her administration
            that the chapter began selling Hadassah Certificates and giving donor credit. The chapters first
            style show was also held during this time.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#sger">Sara Ellen Weisfeld Gerrick</persName> served from <date when="1978">1978</date>1978 to <date when="1980">1980</date>. During her tenure, a donor dinner honoring
            <persName>Sam Lack</persName> was held, and the name of the chapter was changed from <orgName ref="#vch">Valley Chapter</orgName> to <orgName ref="#mvch">McAllen-Valley
               Chapter</orgName>.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#mdav">Marsha Davis</persName> served as President from <date when="1980">1980</date> to ,<date when="1982">1982</date>, during which time the chapter had its
            first art auction in conjunction with Sisterhood-an event that proved very successful. It was also the
            first time that tickets to the annual style show and luncheon were sold to the outside community. A
            donor dinner and Purim Ball were also held.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#sriv">Mrs. Sonia Rivas</persName> presided from <date when="1982">1982</date> to <date when="1984">1984</date>, during which time the chapter hosted its third
            Regional Conference. The chapter also printed the first Temple Directory, in conjunction with <orgName ref="#bnbr">B'nai B'rith</orgName>, a project that continues today.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#mdav">Marsha Davis</persName> again served as President in 1984-5, and <persName ref="#dwil">Dahlia Wilk</persName> in 1985-87. Under that
            administration, the chapter began selling HEB Gift Certificates (Nifty Giftys), which are still being
            sold today.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#cher">Charlene Hertz</persName> once again assumed the role of President in <date notBefore="1987" notAfter="1988">1987-88</date>, during which time the
            chapter had a very successful fashion show and luncheon at the <orgName ref="#mcc">McAllen Country Club</orgName>, featuring professional
            models from <placeName ref="#dal">Dallas</placeName>.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#dwil">Dahlia Wilk</persName> served again in <date notBefore="1988" notAfter="1989">1988-89</date>, during which time a second style show featuring the professional
            models was held at the country club.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#cher">Charlene</persName> returned to the presidency in <date notBefore="1989" notAfter="1990">1989-90</date>, followed by <persName ref="#lwur">Leonore Wurtzcl</persName>, who moved
               shortly after beginning her term. <persName ref="#rwei3">Rosalie Weisfeld</persName> took over as President at that time and served uutil
            <date when="1992">1992</date>.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#riba">Rae Marie Ibarra</persName> served from <date notBefore="1992" notAfter="1994">1992-94</date>, followed by <persName ref="#alip">Annette Lipshitz</persName> in <date notBefore="1994" notAfter="1996">1994-1996</date>, when the
            chapter sponsored a symposium on cancer research for area doctors with an Israeli doctor facilitating.
            The chapter also held its first blood drive in conjunction with the <placeName ref="#tema">Temple</placeName>.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#rhoh">Roberta Hohensteis</persName> serving as President for <date notBefore="1996" notAfter="1998">1996-98</date>, during which time the fashion show was
            re-instituted very successfully at <placeName ref="#cac">the Club at Cimarron</placeName> in <placeName ref="#miss">Mission</placeName>. The chapter sponsored a very successful
               Walk-a-Thon for Breast Cancer in memory of <persName ref="#sger">Sara Ellen Gerrick</persName>, and well-attended fundraising
               dinner in honor of <persName ref="#mblu">Michael J. Blum</persName>.</p>
         <p>The chapter has continued to flourish, despite a few years in which a President could not be
            secured. But during those times, Past Presidents stepped in to fill in the gaps and help the chapter
            meet its quotas. Following those few difficult periods, the chapter persevered and continued to thrive.
            It is now a healthy and active organization.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
